<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD DocBook XML V5.0-Based Extension//EN"
	"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/freebsd50.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: head/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/vm-design/article.xml 43184 2013-11-13 07:52:45Z hrs $ -->
<!-- FreeBSD Documentation Project -->
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">

  <info><title>CM120 Operation Instruction</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author><personname>
	<firstname>Chen</firstname>
	<surname>Xu</surname>
		</personname>
	<affiliation>
	  <address>
	    <email>Chen.Xu@umassmed.edu</email>
	  </address>
	</affiliation></author>
    </authorgroup>

    
   <abstract>
		<para>We no longer use film for TEM exposure anymore! Instead, we use digital
			camera. There are basically two types of digital cameras available on the
			market for TEM applications - Charge-Coupled Device (<acronym>CCD</acronym>)
			and Direct Electron Detector. On CM120, there are two cameras installed - Gatan
			Orius model 832 and Tietz TemCam 224-HD. They both are <acronym>CCD</acronym>
			type of cameras. In this document, I give information about basic properties of
			the cameras, how to use them with CM120 and specific technical note for why we
			need use them in such way.  </para>

		<para>It also lists pixelsize inforamtion for both cameras so you can decide
			which magnification you want to use for your final image. I also try to show
			you how to use <application>SerialEM</application> to control them.</para>

		<para><link xlink:href="article.pdf">A pdf version of this document</link> is
			also available.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>


  <sect1> <title xml:id="basic-properties">Some Basic Properties of the Two Cameras</title>

			<para>Here are two images of the cameras on CM120.</para>

			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="Orius-831"/> 
			  </imageobject>

			  <textobject>
				<literallayout class="monospaced">+---------------+ 
			|       A       |
			+---------------+</literallayout>
			  </textobject>

			  <textobject>
				<phrase>A picture</phrase> 
			  </textobject>
			</mediaobject>

			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="224HD"/> 
			  </imageobject>

			  <textobject>
				<literallayout class="monospaced">+---------------+ 
			|       A       |
			+---------------+</literallayout>
			  </textobject>

			  <textobject>
				<phrase>A picture</phrase> 
			  </textobject>
			</mediaobject>

			<para>This table lists some important propertt parameters:</para>

			<informaltable pgwide="1">
			  <tgroup cols="3">
				<thead>
				  <row>
					<entry>Property</entry>
					<entry>Gatan Orius 832</entry>
					<entry>Tietz TemCam 224-HD</entry>
				  </row>
				</thead>

				<tbody>
				  <row>
				<entry>Format</entry>
				<entry>4008 x 2672</entry>
				<entry>2048 x 2048</entry>
				  </row>

				  <row>
				<entry>Pixel Size on Chip(&mu;m)</entry>
				<entry>9.0</entry>
				<entry>24.0</entry>
				  </row>

				  <row>
				<entry>Digitization</entry>
				<entry>14-bit </entry>
				<entry>16-bit</entry>
				  </row>

				  <row>
				<entry>Light Coupling Mechanism</entry>
				<entry>Fiber Optic</entry>
				<entry>Fiber Optic</entry>
				  </row>
				  
				<row>
				<entry>Mounting Position</entry>
				<entry>sided-mount via 35mm port</entry>
				<entry>bottom-mount</entry>
				  </row>
				</tbody>
			  </tgroup>
			</informaltable>

			<para>You can find more information about these two cameras from vendor's
				datasheets for <link xlink:href="TemCam-F224HD.pdf">F224-HD </link> and <link
				xlink:href="http://www.gatan.com/products/tem-imaging-spectroscopy/orius-cameras
				">Gatan Orius</link>.</para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1> <title xml:id="shutter-control-info">Shutter Control - Background Inforamtion</title> 

		<para>Shutter control usually means TEM shutter control by hardware or software
			of digital camera. The purpose, in most cases, is to have no beam on camera
			except exposure period. Not all camera reaquires having TEM shutter control to
			get an image. For cryoEM applications where accurate dose is to be concerned,
			it makes a lot of sense to have shutter control. Fortunitely, most of high-end
			digital cameras for TEM have TEM shutter control support. </para>

		<para>The shutter discussed here is not any kind of mechanical shutter.
			Instead, it is electronic. If an alignment coil in TEM column is put to a "bad"
			value, then the beam disppears due to misalignment. We call it shutter closed.
			And we call it open when the good alignment coil current is restored. Therefore,
			this kind of electronic shutter can open and close very quickly.</para>

		<para>An exposure on film requires no beam before film is pushed in to final
			location and stablized; and it opens shutter to let beam shine on film to
			expose and then shutter is closed again when exposure finishes. On FEI
			microscope with Low Dose funtionality, one can even define pre-expose time. In
			this case, two shuttes are required to work together - first shutter above
			specimen opens to have beam pre-expose on sample for certain period of time,
			then second shutter below specimen opens to start exposure on film. Usually, the two
			alignment coils to be controlled as upper and lower shutters are Gun Upper coil
			and a Film Shutter Coil next to projector lens. All this is done within FEI
			software control for when and which shutter is open or close. We usually call this
			internal shutter control.</para>

		<para> To image with a digital camera, especially for a beam sensitive
			specimen, shutter control is therefore also needed. If configured correctly,
			when camera is inserted and large screen of TEM is lifted, the beam should be
			blanked. This shutter control is achieved by changing the same alignment coils
			using shutter cable(s) from camera controller. The shutter cable directly
			connects to TEM hardware so that when large screen is lifted, an extra voltage
			is sent to TEM coil to "screw up" a good alignment. Thus, beam is blanked. If
			we need to pre-expose our sample for whatever reason, then two cables will be
			needed - one for pre-specimen and one for post-specimen. This control is done
			by using external hardware. We normally call this "external" shutter control as
			it is not via TEM software. </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> 
	<title xml:id="shutter-control-setup">Shutter Control Setup for Orius 831 and TemCam 
		224HD</title>


  </sect1>
</article>

