<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD DocBook XML V5.0-Based Extension//EN"
	"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/freebsd50.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: head/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/vm-design/article.xml 43184 2013-11-13 07:52:45Z hrs $ -->
<!-- FreeBSD Documentation Project -->
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">

  <info><title>CM120 Operation Instruction</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author><personname>
	<firstname>Chen</firstname>
	<surname>Xu</surname>
		</personname>
	<affiliation>
	  <address>
	    <email>Chen.Xu@umassmed.edu</email>
	  </address>
	</affiliation></author>
    </authorgroup>

    
   <abstract>
		<para>We no longer use film for TEM exposure anymore! Instead, we use digital
			camera. There are basically two types of digital cameras available on the
			market for TEM applications - <acronym>CCD</acronym> and Direct Electron
			Detector. On CM120, there are two cameras installed - Gatan Orius model 832 and
			Tietz TemCam 224-HD. They both are <acronym>CCD</acronym> type of cameras. In
			this document, I give information about basic properties of the cameras, how to
			use them with CM120 and specific technical note for why we need use them in
			such way.  </para>

		<para>It also lists pixelsize inforamtion for both cameras so you can decide
			which magnification you want to use for your final image. I also try to show
			you how to use <application>SerialEM</application> to control them.</para>

		<para><link xlink:href="article.pdf">A pdf version of this document</link> is
			also available.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>


  <sect1> <title xml:id="basic-properties">Some Basic Properties of the Two Cameras</title>

			<para>Here are two images of the cameras on CM120.</para>

			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="Orius-831"/> 
			  </imageobject>

			  <textobject>
				<literallayout class="monospaced">+---------------+ 
			|       A       |
			+---------------+</literallayout>
			  </textobject>

			  <textobject>
				<phrase>A picture</phrase> 
			  </textobject>
			</mediaobject>

			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="224HD"/> 
			  </imageobject>

			  <textobject>
				<literallayout class="monospaced">+---------------+ 
			|       A       |
			+---------------+</literallayout>
			  </textobject>

			  <textobject>
				<phrase>A picture</phrase> 
			  </textobject>
			</mediaobject>

			<para>This table lists some important propertt parameters:</para>

			<informaltable pgwide="1">
			  <tgroup cols="3">
				<thead>
				  <row>
					<entry>Property</entry>
					<entry>Gatan Orius 832</entry>
					<entry>Tietz TemCam 224-HD</entry>
				  </row>
				</thead>

				<tbody>
				  <row>
				<entry>Format</entry>
				<entry>4008 x 2672</entry>
				<entry>2048 x 2048</entry>
				  </row>

				  <row>
				<entry>Pixel Size on Chip(&mu;m)</entry>
				<entry>9.0</entry>
				<entry>24.0</entry>
				  </row>

				  <row>
				<entry>Digitization</entry>
				<entry>14-bit </entry>
				<entry>16-bit</entry>
				  </row>

				  <row>
				<entry>Light Coupling Mechanism</entry>
				<entry>Fiber Optic</entry>
				<entry>Fiber Optic</entry>
				  </row>
				  
				<row>
				<entry>Mounting Position</entry>
				<entry>sided-mount via 35mm port</entry>
				<entry>bottom-mount</entry>
				  </row>
				</tbody>
			  </tgroup>
			</informaltable>

			<para>You can find more information about these two cameras from vendor's
				datasheets for <link xlink:href="TemCam-F224HD.pdf">F224-HD </link> and <link
				xlink:href="http://www.gatan.com/products/tem-imaging-spectroscopy/orius-cameras
				">Gatan Orius</link>.</para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1> <title xml:id="shutter-control-info">Shutter Control - Background Inforamtion</title> 

		<para>Shutter control usually means TEM shutter control by hardware or software
			of digital camera. The purpose, in most cases, is to have no beam on camera
			except exposure period. Not all camera reaquires having TEM shutter control to
			get an image. For cryoEM applications where accurate dose is to be concerned,
			it makes a lot of sense to have shutter control. Fortunitely, most of high-end
			digital cameras for TEM have TEM shutter control support. </para>

		<para>The shutter discussed here is not any kind of mechanical shutter.
			Instead, it is electronic. If an alignment coil in TEM column is put to a "bad"
			value, then the beam disppears due to misalignment. We call it shutter closed.
			And we call it open when the good alignment coil current is restored. Therefore,
			this kind of electronic shutter can open and close very quickly.</para>

		<para>An exposure on film requires no beam before film is pushed in to final
			location and stablized; and it opens shutter to let beam shine on film to
			expose and then shutter is closed again when exposure finishes. On FEI
			microscope with Low Dose funtionality, one can even define pre-expose time. In
			this case, two shuttes are required to work together - first shutter above
			specimen opens to have beam pre-expose on sample for certain period of time,
			then second shutter below specimen opens to start exposure on film. Usually, the two
			alignment coils to be controlled as upper and lower shutters are Gun Upper coil
			and a Film Shutter Coil next to projector lens. All this is done within FEI
			software control for when and which shutter is open or close. We usually call this
			internal shutter control.</para>

		<para> To image with a digital camera, especially for a beam sensitive
			specimen, shutter control is therefore also needed. If configured correctly,
			when camera is inserted and large screen of TEM is lifted, the beam should be
			blanked. This shutter control is achieved by changing the same alignment coils
			using shutter cable(s) from camera controller. The shutter cable directly
			connects to TEM hardware so that when large screen is lifted, an extra voltage
			is sent to TEM coil to "screw up" a good alignment. Thus, beam is blanked. If
			we need to pre-expose our sample for whatever reason, then two cables will be
			needed - one for pre-specimen and one for post-specimen. This control is done
			by using external hardware. We normally call this "external" shutter control as
			it is not via TEM software. </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title xml:id="shutter-control-setup">Shutter Control Setup for Orius 831 and TemCam 224HD</title></sect1>

  <sect1><title>Apply High Tension</title>
      <para> Turn High Tension (H.T.) on if it is off by pressing the
          <guibutton>[&nbsp;H.T.&nbsp;]</guibutton> button on the panel. From
          <guibutton>[&nbsp;Parameter&nbsp;]</guibutton> page, set it to 120kV or
          the voltage you want. </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Turn filament on</title>
        <para> It is recommended to turn the filament on while on the
            <guibutton>[&nbsp;configuration&nbsp;]</guibutton> page where the
            actual filament current number is shown and the
            <guibutton>[&nbsp;limit&nbsp;]</guibutton> can be
            checked(highlighted).  </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check saturation and gun tilt, and then saturate the filament.</title>
	  <para> The procedure is as following:.  </para>

     <itemizedlist> 
      <listitem> <para> Desaturate the filament about 2-3 clicks.  </para> </listitem>
      <listitem> <para> Press <guibutton>[&nbsp;Align&nbsp;]</guibutton> button, highlight <guibutton>[&nbsp;Gun Tilt&nbsp;]</guibutton>.  </para> </listitem>
      <listitem> <para> Adjust the <guibutton>[&nbsp;multi-function X, Y&nbsp;]</guibutton>
          				to get the best shape for the tip and maximum intensity as well. </para> </listitem>
      <listitem> <para> Bring the filament current to saturation.  </para> </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check C2 aperture mechanical position and C2 stigmatism</title>
    <para> Steps to adjust the C2 aperture mechanical position are:  </para>
	
    <itemizedlist> 
    	<listitem> <para> Make sure the C2 aperture is in.  </para> </listitem>

      <listitem>
            <para> At around 5kX, cross the beam first and center beam
                using deflectors (<guibutton>[&nbsp;Beam Shift
                    X,Y&nbsp;]</guibutton>), then spread the beam until its
                diameter is close to 5cm ring on the screen. Adjust
                screws X &amp; Y on C2 aperture to center the beam.
                Repeat this process 2-3 times.  </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem> 
            <para> At high mag ~30kX or higher, change the
                <guibutton>[&nbsp;intensity&nbsp;]</guibutton> of beam(C2) through
                the crossover and adjust the screws X,Y to make the beam
                symmetric when spreading out.  </para>
      </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
          <para> 
            There are two ways to check and adjust the <userinput>C2</userinput> stigmatism:
          </para>
        <itemizedlist> 
          <listitem> 
            <para> When the filament is desaturated, press
              <guibutton>[&nbsp;Stig&nbsp;]</guibutton> button and select
              <guibutton>[&nbsp;Cond&nbsp;]</guibutton>, then adjust
              <guibutton>[&nbsp;Multi-function knobs&nbsp;]</guibutton> so that the details in the filament
              shadowing image can be clearest and sharpest.  </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem> 
            <para> When changing the beam intensity, use the
              <guibutton>[&nbsp;Multi-function knobs&nbsp;]</guibutton> to adjust the beam into symmetric and
              "round" shape, i.e. not elliptical.  </para>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
			
			<note>
				<para>For this purpose, don't pay attention to the beam shape when beam is
				exactly at cross point, as that more reflects the shape of the crystal tip,
				rather than stigmatism. You want to make beam "round" when spreat
				out. </para> 
			</note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check specimen holder &amp; load grid</title>

      <important>
        <para> This is important. If you see any problem with any of the
            holders, report it to the manager
            <emphasis>immediately</emphasis>. Otherwise, you could be
            the one held accountable for the damage. Several details
            about the holder must be checked carefully before use:
        </para>
        </important>
   <itemizedlist> 
   	<listitem> <para> Overall shape is good, and there is not obvious damage.  </para> </listitem>

	<listitem> 
        <para> Make sure there is no crack or any other damage on the
            O-ring. If you do see a damage, like a cut etc., ask manager
            to replace it for you. Check if there any dirt or fibril on
            the O-ring. You might want to clean it gently with alcohol
            and slightly re-grease it. Do not over-grease. The main
            function of the grease is to lubricate. </para>
	</listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

      <para> Gently secure the specimen grid on its position. Use the
        tool pin to open and close the clamping device.  </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Insert specimen holder into column</title>
	<warning>
    <para> Be careful! Only at this stage, you might damage the scope or
      specimen holder <emphasis>mechanically</emphasis>. Be sure that
      you understand what you are doing. Should you feel any confusion
      about this procedure, please stop and ask for help.  </para>
	</warning>

	<note>
		<para> For the sake of filament crystal, it is REQUIRED to turn down the
		filament to <emphasis>10</emphasis> before inserting the specimen rod. That way, in case
		<userinput>IGP</userinput> shoots high, there will be no subtancial damage to
		the LaB6 tip crystal. In general, filament should be kept at
		<emphasis>10</emphasis> or completely off until <userinput>IGP</userinput>
		recovers to below <emphasis>26</emphasis>.  </para>
    </note>

		<para>The procedure to insert a room temperature specimen rod is below.</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem> <para> define airlock pumping time as 60 seconds, from Vacuum - Cryo page.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Reset stage tilt angle to 0 if it is not.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Insert rod in, with the Pin at 3'oclock position. </para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> As soon as it reach the end, rotate rod CLOCKWISE with some pushing force 
							so that the pin slides into the locking groove at 5'oclock position. You should feel the
							rod goes "in" about 8mm.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Wait until the red LED on the stage disappears. Dismiss the "non-standard" 
							flushing message on the screen by pressing "Reset" button at lower left corner of the screen display. </para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Turn rod Count-Clockwise until pin is at 12'oclock position, while watching 
		<userinput>IGP</userinput> reading. You should adjust your rotating speed to keep <userinput>IGP</userinput> &lt; <emphasis>40</emphasis>. </para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Adjust the specimen height to the eucentric height</title>
		<para>Eucentricity is a fixed reference point in a scope. It is the
			intercross point of stage axis and column axis. We want to observe our specimen
			grid at this height level so that the actual magnification doesn't differ much
			from day to day. And scope is designed to perform better when specimen is at
			such height. It is good to have the habbit to always adjust specimen to eucentric
			height after rod insertion. On CM120, the procedure is as following:</para>

		<itemizedlist> 
		<listitem> <para> Have beam seen on large screen, at ~3000X, and find a feature on the grid.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> rotate stage back and forth by pressing <guibutton>[&nbsp;CompuStage&nbsp;]</guibutton> - <guibutton>[&nbsp;A-wobbler&nbsp;]</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Adjust <userinput>joystick Z</userinput> to minimize the shifting of the feature.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check Beam Tilt Pivot Point X, Y</title>

      <note> 
		<para> The prerequisites for Pivot-Point is specimen being at eucentric height
		and objective being preceisly at focus level.  </para> 
      </note>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem> <para> Make sure the specimen is at eucentric height.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Take out Obj. aperture.  </para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Press button <guibutton>[&nbsp;Align&nbsp;]</guibutton> - <guibutton>[&nbsp;Direct Alignment&nbsp;]</guibutton> - <guibutton>[&nbsp;Beam Tilt Pivot X&nbsp;]</guibutton>.</para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Merge image feature by adjusting <guibutton>[&nbsp;Focus&nbsp;]</guibutton> knob. This is to <emphasis>precisely</emphasis> focus the image.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Merge beam using <guibutton>[&nbsp;Multi-fcuntion knobs&nbsp;]</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem> <para> Repeat the last two steps for <guibutton>[&nbsp;Beam Tilt Pivot Y&nbsp;]</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem> <para> Press <guibutton>[&nbsp;Align&nbsp;]</guibutton> button again to exit.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1> <title>Check voltage and current rotation centers </title>
		<para> This step is to align the beam to make it parallel to the axis
		of the column. The purpose of this step is to make beam to hit specimen
		perpendicularly. A coma is not a good thing, as it generates some phase
		error to the data.  </para>

		<para>The procedure is below.</para>

	<itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem> <para> Press <guibutton>[&nbsp;Align&nbsp;]</guibutton> button and select <guibutton>[&nbsp;Rotation Center&nbsp;]</guibutton>.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> Select <guibutton>[&nbsp;Voltage&nbsp;]</guibutton> or <guibutton>[&nbsp;Current&nbsp;]</guibutton> from the same page.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> Adjust the <guibutton>[&nbsp;Multi-function Knobs&nbsp;]</guibutton> to let the wobbling be symmetrical around the center of the beam. The feature at very center of the large screen has minimum shift.</para> </listitem>
  	  <listitem> <para> If you perform this with Obj aperture in, then re-check the certering of objective aperture.</para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<note> 
	  <para> The step size button on <guibutton>[&nbsp;Focus&nbsp;]</guibutton> is
		used to control the amplitude of the beam wobbling.  </para>

	  <para> The steps used here only give "roughly" parallel beam to the axis.
		If you need very acurate "0" tilt beam, a different alignment procedure -
		Coma-Free is needed.  </para>
	</note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Put in objective aperture and center it</title>
		<para> It is important to know what size of the  obj.  aperture you are
			using. You don't want to use too small size to actual cut off useful high
			resolution signal. Meantime, you don't want to use the aperture size too large,
			as the non-usable high resoltion beam becomes noise to your image. This reduces
			signal to noise ration unneccesarily. </para>

		<para>The position of the aperture could affect the obj. lens stigmatism.
			Therefore, you want to do this step before you finally check Obj lens
			stigmatism. </para>

		<para>Here are the steps to insert and center Objective lens aperture: </para>

	<itemizedlist> 
		<listitem> <para> Make sure the large screen is down, to prevent CCD from damage.  </para> </listitem>
	   	<listitem> <para> Switch to diffraction mode by pressing the diffraction "D" button.  </para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Adjust camera length to ~1m using magnification knob. </para></listitem>
	   	<listitem> <para> Adjust the <guibutton>[&nbsp;Intensity&nbsp;]</guibutton> (C2) and <guibutton>[&nbsp;Defocus&nbsp;]</guibutton> 
					knobs to see the shape edge of the obj. aperture.  </para> </listitem>
	    <listitem> <para> Adjust the related mechanical screws on aperture holder to choose the proper size of the aperture and 
					center it to the central beam on diffraction pattern.  </para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Switch back to image mode by pressing <guibutton>[&nbsp;D&nbsp;]</guibutton> button again.  </para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check Objective Lens stigmatism</title>

		<para> The obj. stigmatism should be corrected as much as possible, and
			it should be checked for <emphasis>every</emphasis> netative stain low-dose
			image that you are taking, as staining material might change field in local 
			area.  This is a bit hard by hand. Even with lastest version 
			of SerialEW, this can be done by software, it is still not easy and time 
			efficient. However, slight stigmated image is not critically bad, as 
			it can be corrected as part of CTF correction computationally. </para>

 		<para> Here are steps to correct Obj lens stigmatism, manually:</para>

	<itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem> <para> Go to a relatively high mag., such as 100,000X, and focus the image.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> If possible, acquire continous CCD image with live FFT so Thon rings can be seen.</para></listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> Press the <guibutton>[&nbsp;Stig&nbsp;]</guibutton> button, highlight
        <guibutton>[&nbsp;Obj&nbsp;]</guibutton>, and select proper stepsize.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> Adjust the stigmatism using <guibutton>[&nbsp;Multi-function knobs&nbsp;]</guibutton> until it
        becomes minimum at all defocus levels. (It shows up more at close to focus.) </para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Typical Low-Dose setup parameters</title>
		<para> Here are some typical setup for Low-Dose condition.  </para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem> <para> Search: Mag=2650X(3000X with screen up), Spotsize=3-5, image mode </para>

			<para> Alternatively, at 2650-3400x, switch to Diff. mode by pressing
				"Diff" button.  Adjust camera length to 680mm using "Mag" knob.  Focus the
				diffraction spot using <guibutton>[&nbsp;Focus&nbsp;]</guibutton> knob, and then adjust
				"defocus" until the image inside central spot expands to proper size.
				Personally, I like to "defocus" to clockwise side. What you got is a shadowing
				image inside of defocused diffraction central beam. The advantage of this is
				high contrast compared to a normal image mode.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para> Focus: Mag=175kX, Spotsize=6. When work with tilting stage,
				make sure S1 or S2 sits on tilting axis of the geonimeter, the angles will posted on
				the panel.  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem> <para> Record: Mag=53000X(60kX), spotsize=3-5 </para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Align an identified area under <guibutton>[&nbsp;Exposure&nbsp;]</guibutton> and <guibutton>[&nbsp;Search&nbsp;]</guibutton></title>
	    <para>
		  This step is to insure that what you see under low mag. (Search
		  mode) will be the same area you get under imaging mag. Here is how
		  I do it: </para>

	<itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem> <para> At Exposure mode, MECHANICALLY drive an identified spot to the centber of the screen.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> 
		<para> At Search mode(and usually in Diffraction mode also), using the
			<guibutton>[&nbsp;Multi-function knobs&nbsp;]</guibutton> to backtrack the identified
			spot at the center of the screen (electronically). This uses Image Shift or
			Diffaction Shift (when Search mode is set up in Diff mode) to "shift" image
			without actually moving the stage position.  </para> </listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>

	  <note>
	    <para> You can use a corner of a mesh as the identified spot for a
		  negative stain specimet or to use an ice burn mark in the cryo
		  case.  </para>
	  </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check S1 and S2 parameters</title>
	    <para> In Focus mode, S1 and S2 are linked to the positions of the beam
		  which is deflected away from the center of the imaging area on the
		  specimen. When highlighted, their parameters can be changed by the
		  Multi-function keys.  </para>

	    <para> Normally, we use 175kX as the magnification. The radius of the
		  spot is about 1.5 microns. Depending on the specimen, you can change those
		  parameters to fit your needs.  </para>
  </sect1>

	<sect1><title>Finishing Up</title>
		<para> When you are done with your session, perform finishing up procedure.</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem> <para> Specimen rod out.</para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Reset Stage Position, X, Y, Z and A.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Filament 0.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> H.T. OFF.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Cryo-cycle, normally for 2-3 hours.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Data display OFF.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Display OFF.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Log your session on logbook.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>

</article>

