<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD DocBook XML V4.2-Based Extension//EN"
	"../../../share/xml/freebsd42.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % entities PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//ENTITIES DocBook FreeBSD Entity Set//EN" "../../share/xml/entities.ent">
<!ENTITY tem.f20 "<emphasis>Tecnai F20</emphasis>">
<!ENTITY tem.f30 "<emphasis>Tecnai F30</emphasis>">
<!ENTITY cm120 "<emphasis>CM120</emphasis>">
%entities;
]>


<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>CM120 Operation Instruction</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Chen</firstname>
      <surname>Xu</surname>
      <affiliation>
		<address><email>Chen.Xu@umassmed.edu</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

   <pubdate>
2016-02-27 11:58:13
   </pubdate>

    <abstract>
		<para> This document tries to list steps and procedures for a typical
		daily operation on &cm120;. You can use it as guidebook to help you when you
		are sitting with &cm120;, especially if you are a new user. I here assume you
		are already familiar with scope interface, what the knobs and buttons do etc..
		You might use the section titles as quick bullet points, but the explanation
		inside each sections are supposed to be useful and informative.  <ulink
		url="article.pdf">A pdf version of this document</ulink> is also available.
		</para>

		<para>If you have suggestion how to improve this document to make it more
		useful, please feel free to let me know. Thank you! </para>  

		<para>NOTE: all the turning knobs on the panel and push buttons are
		marked in <strong>Bold</strong>.</para>
    </abstract>

  </articleinfo>


  <sect1> <title>Check log book to see if there have been any problems</title>

    <para> It is always a good idea to check the LOG book. You can find
      useful information listed there, such as: </para>

    <itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem> <para> If there have been any recent problems with the scope.  </para> </listitem>
      <listitem> <para> The conditions that were used last, especially the filament saturation.  </para> </listitem>
      <listitem> <para> Any special note that last user wants you to know. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1> <title>Check vacuum status</title> 

    <para> The status must be <emphasis>Ready</emphasis> before you can operate the scope.
      If not, you should ask for help and report it to the manager.
      Usually, if the vacuum is not ready, it is due to one of the
      following reasons: </para>

	<itemizedlist> 
	   <listitem> <para> The scope is malfunctioning.  </para> </listitem>
	   <listitem> <para> The air pressure is not within a good range(the building compressed air may be down?). </para> </listitem>
	   <listitem> <para> The cooling water is off.  </para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Vacuum being <emphasis>Ready</emphasis> means:</para>

	<itemizedlist> 
		<listitem> <para> Top line of vacuum page shows "ready". </para> </listitem>  
		<listitem> <para> <devicename>P3</devicename> &lt; 50,  <devicename>IGP</devicename> &lt; 26 (normally, they are shown 0, 5).</para> </listitem> 
		<listitem> <para> LEDs for UVAC and HiVAC are lit. </para> </listitem> 
	</itemizedlist>  	
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1> <title>Add Liquid Nitrogen to the BIG anti-contaminator dewar</title>
    
		<para> LN2 in the cold trap dewar is necessary for fast vacuum recovery.
		It is very useful, especially when you need to change grids and/or do a cryo
		session. However, if you are working with a negative stain or plastic section - a
		dry grid, the scope can still run without LN2 cold trap. Unless you are running
		automatic, long overnight session, you should always use it. </para>
    
    <note> <para> Generally, when you first put LN2 dewar to its stand, you want to
		be SLOW, or the strong evaporation will make LN2 spilling.  </para> </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1><title>Apply High Tension</title>
	  <para> Turn High Tension (H.T.) on if it is off by pressing the
		<strong>H.T.</strong> button on the panel. From
		<strong>Parameter</strong> page, set it to 120kV or the voltage you
		want. </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Turn filament on</title>
		<para> It is recommended to turn the filament on while on the
		<strong>configuration</strong> page where the actual filament current
		number is shown and the <strong>limit</strong> can be
		checked(highlighted).  </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check saturation and gun tilt, and then saturate the filament.</title>
	  <para> The procedure is as following:.  </para>

     <itemizedlist> 
      <listitem> <para> Desaturate the filament about 2-3 clicks.  </para> </listitem>
      <listitem> <para> Press <strong>Align</strong> button, highlight <strong>Gun Tilt</strong>.  </para> </listitem>
      <listitem> <para> Adjust the <strong>multi-function X, Y</strong>
          				to get the best shape for the tip and maximum intensity as well. </para> </listitem>
      <listitem> <para> Bring the filament current to saturation.  </para> </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check C2 aperture mechanical position and C2 stigmatism</title>
    <para> Steps to adjust the C2 aperture mechanical position are:  </para>
	
    <itemizedlist> 
    	<listitem> <para> Make sure the C2 aperture is in.  </para> </listitem>

      <listitem>
			<para> At around 5kX, cross the beam first and center beam using deflectors
			(<strong>Beam Shift X,Y</strong>), then spread the beam until its
			diameter is close to 5cm ring on the screen. Adjust screws X &amp; Y on C2
			aperture to center the beam.  Repeat this process 2-3 times.  </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem> 
			<para> At high mag ~30kX or higher, change the
			<strong>intensity</strong> of beam(C2) through the crossover and
			adjust the screws X & Y to make the beam symmetric when spreading out.  </para>
      </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
          <para> 
            There are two ways to check and adjust the <devicename>C2</devicename> stigmatism:
          </para>
        <itemizedlist> 
          <listitem> 
            <para> When the filament is desaturated, press
              <strong>Stig</strong> button and select
              <strong>Cond</strong>, then adjust
              <strong>Multi-function knobs</strong> so that the details in the filament
              shadowing image can be clearest and sharpest.  </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem> 
            <para> When changing the beam intensity, use the
              <strong>Multi-function knobs</strong> to adjust the beam into symmetric and
              "round" shape, i.e. not elliptical.  </para>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
			
			<note>
				<para>For this purpose, don't pay attention to the beam shape when beam is
				exactly at cross point, as that more reflects the shape of the crystal tip,
				rather than stigmatism. You want to make beam "round" when spreat
				out. </para> 
			</note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check specimen holder &amp; load grid</title>
  
		<para> This is important. If you see any problem with any of the holders,
		report it to the manager <emphasis>immediately</emphasis>. Otherwise, you could
		be the one held accountable for the damage. Several details about the holder
		must be checked carefully before use: </para>

   <itemizedlist> 
   	<listitem> <para> Overall shape is good, and there is not obvious damage.  </para> </listitem>

	<listitem> 
		<para> Make sure there is no crack or any other damage on the O-ring. If you
		do see a damage, like a cut etc., ask manager to replace it for you. Check if
		there any dirt or fibril on the O-ring. You might want to clean it gently
		with alcohol and slightly re-grease it. Do not over-grease. The main function
		of the grease is to lubricate. </para>
	</listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

      <para> Gently secure the specimen grid on its position. Use the
        tool pin to open and close the clamping device.  </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Insert specimen holder into column</title>
	<important>
    <para> Be careful! Only at this stage, you might damage the scope or
      specimen holder <emphasis>mechanically</emphasis>. Be sure that
      you understand what you are doing. Should you feel any confusion
      about this procedure, please stop and ask for help.  </para>
	</important>

	<note>
		<para> For the sake of filament crystal, it is REQUIRED to turn down the
		filament to <emphasis>10</emphasis> before inserting the specimen rod. That way, in case
		<devicename>IGP</devicename> shoots high, there will be no subtancial damage to
		the LaB6 tip crystal. In general, filament should be kept at
		<emphasis>10</emphasis> or completely off until <devicename>IGP</devicename>
		recovers to below <emphasis>26</emphasis>.  </para>
    </note>

		<para>The procedure to insert a room temperature specimen rod is below.</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem> <para> define airlock pumping time as 60 seconds, from Vacuum - Cryo page.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Reset stage tilt angle to 0 if it is not.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Insert rod in, with the Pin at 3'oclock position. </para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> As soon as it reach the end, rotate rod CLOCKWISE with some pushing force 
							so that the pin slides into the locking groove at 5'oclock position. You should feel the
							rod goes "in" about 8mm.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Wait until the red LED on the stage disappears. Dismiss the "non-standard" 
							flushing message on the screen by pressing "Reset" button at lower left corner of the screen display. </para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Turn rod Counter-Clockwise until pin is at 12'oclock position, while watching 
		<devicename>IGP</devicename> reading. You should adjust your rotating speed to keep <devicename>IGP</devicename> &lt; <emphasis>40</emphasis>. </para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Adjust the specimen height to the eucentric height</title>
		<para>Eucentricity is a fixed reference point in a scope. It is the
			intercross point of stage axis and column axis. We want to observe our specimen
			grid at this height level so that the actual magnification doesn't differ much
			from day to day. And scope is designed to perform better when specimen is at
			such height. It is good to have the habbit to always adjust specimen to eucentric
			height after rod insertion. On &cm120;, the procedure is as following:</para>

		<itemizedlist> 
		<listitem> <para> Have beam seen on large screen, at ~3000X, and find a feature on the grid.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> rotate stage back and forth by pressing <strong>CompuStage</strong> - <strong>A-wobbler</strong>.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Adjust <devicename>joystick Z</devicename> to minimize the shifting of the feature.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check Beam Tilt Pivot Point X, Y</title>

      <note> 
		<para> The prerequisites for Pivot-Point is specimen being at eucentric height
		and objective being preceisly at focus level.  </para> 
      </note>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem> <para> Make sure the specimen is at eucentric height.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Take out Obj. aperture.  </para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Press button <strong>Align</strong> - <strong>Direct Alignment</strong> - <strong>Beam Tilt Pivot X</strong>.</para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Merge image feature by adjusting <strong>Focus</strong> knob. This is to <emphasis>precisely</emphasis> focus the image.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Merge beam using <strong>Multi-fcuntion knobs</strong>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem> <para> Repeat the last two steps for <strong>Beam Tilt Pivot Y</strong>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem> <para> Press <strong>Align</strong> button again to exit.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1> <title>Check voltage and current rotation centers </title>
		<para> This step is to align the beam to make it parallel to the axis
		of the column. The purpose of this step is to make beam to hit specimen
		perpendicularly. A coma is not a good thing, as it generates some phase
		error to the data.  </para>

		<para>The procedure is below.</para>

	<itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem> <para> Press <strong>Align</strong> button and select <strong>Rotation Center</strong>.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> Select <strong>Voltage</strong> or <strong>Current</strong> from the same page.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> Adjust the <strong>Multi-function Knobs</strong> to let the wobbling be symmetrical around the center of the beam. The feature at very center of the large screen has minimum shift.</para> </listitem>
  	  <listitem> <para> If you perform this with Obj aperture in, then re-check the certering of objective aperture.</para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<note> 
	  <para> The step size button on <strong>Focus</strong> is
		used to control the amplitude of the beam wobbling.  </para>

	  <para> The steps used here only give "roughly" parallel beam to the axis.
		If you need very acurate "0" tilt beam, a different alignment procedure -
		Coma-Free is needed.  </para>
	</note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Put in objective aperture and center it</title>
		<para> It is important to know what size of the  obj.  aperture you are
			using. You don't want to use too small size to actual cut off useful high
			resolution signal. Meantime, you don't want to use the aperture size too large,
			as the non-usable high resoltion beam becomes noise to your image. This reduces
			signal to noise ration unneccesarily. </para>

		<para>The position of the aperture could affect the obj. lens stigmatism.
			Therefore, you want to do this step before you finally check Obj lens
			stigmatism. </para>

		<para>Here are the steps to insert and center Objective lens aperture: </para>

	<itemizedlist> 
		<listitem> <para> Make sure the large screen is down, to prevent CCD from damage.  </para> </listitem>
	   	<listitem> <para> Switch to diffraction mode by pressing the diffraction "D" button.  </para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Adjust camera length to ~1m using magnification knob. </para></listitem>
	   	<listitem> <para> Adjust the <strong>Intensity</strong> (C2) and <strong>Defocus</strong> 
					knobs to see the shape edge of the obj. aperture.  </para> </listitem>
	    <listitem> <para> Adjust the related mechanical screws on aperture holder to choose the proper size of the aperture and 
					center it to the central beam on diffraction pattern.  </para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Switch back to image mode by pressing <strong>D</strong> button again.  </para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check Objective Lens stigmatism</title>

		<para> The obj. stigmatism should be corrected as much as possible, and
			it should be checked for <emphasis>every</emphasis> netative stain low-dose
			image that you are taking, as staining material might change field in local 
			area.  This is a bit hard by hand. Even with lastest version 
			of SerialEW, this can be done by software, it is still not easy and time 
			efficient. However, slight stigmated image is not critically bad, as 
			it can be corrected as part of CTF correction computationally. </para>

 		<para> Here are steps to correct Obj lens stigmatism, manually:</para>

	<itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem> <para> Go to a relatively high mag., such as 100,000X, and focus the image.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> If possible, acquire continous CCD image with live FFT so Thon rings can be seen.</para></listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> Press the <strong>Stig</strong> button, highlight
        <strong>Obj</strong>, and select proper stepsize.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> <para> Adjust the stigmatism using <strong>Multi-function knobs</strong> until it
        becomes minimum at all defocus levels. (It shows up more at close to focus.) </para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Typical Low-Dose setup parameters</title>
		<para> Here are some typical setup for Low-Dose condition.  </para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem> <para> Search: Mag=2650X(3000X with screen up), Spotsize=3-5, image mode </para>

			<para> Alternatively, at 2650-3400x, switch to Diff. mode by pressing
				"Diff" button.  Adjust camera length to 680mm using "Mag" knob.  Focus the
				diffraction spot using <strong>Focus</strong> knob, and then adjust
				"defocus" until the image inside central spot expands to proper size.
				Personally, I like to "defocus" to clockwise side. What you got is a shadowing
				image inside of defocused diffraction central beam. The advantage of this is
				high contrast compared to a normal image mode.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para> Focus: Mag=175kX, Spotsize=6. When work with tilting stage,
				make sure S1 or S2 sits on tilting axis of the geonimeter, the angles will posted on
				the panel.  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem> <para> Record: Mag=53000X(60kX), spotsize=3-5 </para> </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Align an identified area under <strong>Exposure</strong> and <strong>Search</strong></title>
	    <para>
		  This step is to insure that what you see under low mag. (Search
		  mode) will be the same area you get under imaging mag. Here is how
		  I do it: </para>

	<itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem> <para> At Exposure mode, MECHANICALLY drive an identified spot to the centber of the screen.  </para> </listitem>
	  <listitem> 
		<para> At Search mode(and usually in Diffraction mode also), using the
			<strong>Multi-function knobs</strong> to backtrack the identified
			spot at the center of the screen (electronically). This uses Image Shift or
			Diffaction Shift (when Search mode is set up in Diff mode) to "shift" image
			without actually moving the stage position.  </para> </listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>

	  <note>
	    <para> You can use a corner of a mesh as the identified spot for a
		  negative stain specimet or to use an ice burn mark in the cryo
		  case.  </para>
	  </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title>Check S1 and S2 parameters</title>
	    <para> In Focus mode, S1 and S2 are linked to the positions of the beam
		  which is deflected away from the center of the imaging area on the
		  specimen. When highlighted, their parameters can be changed by the
		  Multi-function keys.  </para>

	    <para> Normally, we use 175kX as the magnification. The radius of the
		  spot is about 1.5 microns. Depending on the specimen, you can change those
		  parameters to fit your needs.  </para>
  </sect1>

	<sect1><title>Finishing Up</title>
		<para> When you are done with your session, perform finishing up procedure.</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem> <para> Specimen rod out.</para> </listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Reset Stage Position, X, Y, Z and A.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Filament 0.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> H.T. OFF.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Cryo-cycle, normally for 2-3 hours.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Data display OFF.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Display OFF.</para></listitem>
		<listitem> <para> Log your session on logbook.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>

</article>

